And now
we actually have a surprise. I didn't
know until 2 minutes ago, but we have
Pablo Galindo Salgado, CPython
developer, and David Hewitt presenting
together.
Yes, so please a warm welcome um to
Pablo and David.
>> All right. Okay, what's up? What's up?
Um so I I have a kind of a confession to
make just to explain why we're doing
this talk together. Uh so I have this
this this talk. I I I I'm I'm into
profilers. I do a lot of profilers.
Every time it's like, "Oh, Pablo, are
you doing another profiler?" Yes, yes,
I'm doing that. Uh and I have this talk
about like how to use,
um you know, AI
agents with profilers. So it would tell
you like why things slow. And it was
glorious, but then I I had this
experience. It's like it's like horrible
because I I maintain CPython, right? The
Python language. And then I have this
this this pull request and and and the
AI hated it. It was horrible. Like it
was a horrible experience. So I just
scrapped the whole talk. So like I'm
going to be this like super negative
person because that that would make me
very popular. Uh
so so so this talk is like, uh you know,
slightly negative. So you know, like but
don't worry like, you know, at the end
we are all friends. Uh
So
uh but then something happened.
Something happened. Uh
I'm also a horrible person and I make
the organizers very like nervous because
I I you know, I never sent the actual
like details of the talk. So so not
nothing was published like just my name.
Um and then and then I I find out that
David had the same talk I was doing.
Uh but he could never know that that was
the case because, you know, I I'm a
horrible person. So So I I I was
thinking very hard.
Maybe maybe I should do the right thing
and like we should do the talk together.
And by the power of collaboration and
now we are doing that. Uh so bear with
us as we like go. Yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, clap,
clap. Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
All right, cool, cool. So, presentations
and then we will roll back with the
complaining. It's just 30 minutes of
whining.
Oh, 15. Okay, well, we'll speed run, no
worries. Okay, so so I I I'm I'm into
CPython is just like some language and
like a bunch of profilers and like David
is going to be a little more more
detail, I think.
>> So, yeah.
I was asked whether I was going to give
a talk and I get seems like Pablo and I
were thinking exactly the same thing,
right?
I am an open-source contributor. I work
on Malt C which Samuel already talked
about earlier.
I work with PyDantic as well and PyO3
which bridges the
crosses the bridge between Rust and
Python. So, there three kind of
different levels of projects and they
all have different exposure to AI and
you know the the ecosystem around that.
But, really the observation I had is
that open-source is changing quite fast
as is all of software development.
Wanted to put the expression together
and then lo and behold Pablo and I kind
of thinking exactly the same thing.
>> Yes, yes. Shall I let's go, let's go.
So, so the problem is the following,
right? Like it's an interesting thought.
Let's let's all together very hard.
So, the problem is that like open-source
is driven by maintainers. Normally, we
we are unpaid. Like every time they they
double our salary, but you know the
problem is that we start at zero. So,
that's that's that's not not great.
And the problem is that right now
open-source is just everywhere.
Everything uses open-source. That puts a
lot of pressure on open-source. And the
the landscape is quite changing with
this whole AI and that's what this talk
is about, right? So,
the thing is that this used to be quite
quite cool. It used to be a conversation
where like something submit to PR and
then we kind of review it and and there
is some learning here like you know I I
teach you something like and then you
learn and wow, the power of imagination
now is better. But, now that's not
that's not how it's going because now
you know
people generate PRs and then we review
it and and nothing happens because you
just talk with cloud code by proxy. You
know, you just say, "Hey, hey, why why
you don't change this thing?" And then
the person copy-paste that into cloud
code and then the cloud code changes it.
So, like, you know, I can do that
faster, you know? Like why why is this
So, that one of the problems.
>> And it's like completely the opposite of
what used to happen, right? Like before
all these AI agents, when you actually
received a pull request or a patch, a
contribution, somebody put in time into
thinking about that and you know,
genuine effort. So, then when you
continue that conversation forward, they
have the context. They give you a real
response rather than just going back to
their bot and giving you more and more
and more. And you could have done it
probably with the same bot better.
>> And the the the thing is not just like,
"Oh, well, this should be this way and
you know, I will tell you how to do open
source, just listen to me." Like the
problem is that the this is this the the
thing establishes this beautiful thing
called a connection. You know, humans
like connections. This is very
important. But now there is no
connection. So, like I I don't [__]
want to do this, you know? Like because
I can talk with talk on myself. So, that
that is bad because like then people
won't contribute to open source and then
the project will die, right? You know,
that's the
97% Remember, 97% using open source. So,
we have a problem. Um and the problem is
that we have automated the easy part,
actually easy asterisk, right? Because
I'm pretty sure like people, you know,
contribute to do, I don't know,
Pythontic or Polars will find it quite
difficult at the beginning. But I
believe me when I say this is the actual
easy part, right? The hard part is
something else. It's just actually
knowing what you want to change. Um and
then uh now the the the the
non-important part is the one that like
now we have put the the thing, right?
It's the same thing with AI, like you
know, everybody wants AI to do the
laundry, but like we have automating
art. Well, maybe we we should put them
to the other place, you know?
>> I mean, yeah. Um
>> I agree. I agree with you.
Wow. Wow. You are so intelligent.
>> Sorry.
>> Uh okay. So, so so controversial
question. Is is is open source over?
Like is the is the golden age of open
source over? So, that's what we will
discuss in this in this uh
half a talk that is left. Um so, some
numbers that we put together. So, so
we we are flooded by new people. I I
don't think 36 millions of actual
developers, some of them are clunkers.
Like so so so probably a lot of bots,
but like there is a lot of people that
are joining GitHub and doing stuff,
which is kind of cool because like, you
know, the barrier is lower and a lot of
people that used not to code, now they
code. Like cool. Uh but also like more
more PR's, you know, not that cool.
Um,
you know, you can simplify it this way,
right? Like
with a few enough contributor numbers
it's just infinity.
Um, and the problem is that this is the
the bigger thing, right? Like okay,
remember this. This is an asymmetric
relationship because it takes two
minutes to do the the the, you know,
local interaction, but it takes for me
30 minutes to three hours to review
that. Uh, among other things it's not
just because the code is complicated or
not, it's because like when you
contribute to something like CPython in
particular, which is the language, like
every single line could basically be a
security problem. And guess who is going
to be called? Uh, so so I want to be
very specific. And and the problem is
that again, like I spend three hours on
this or 30 minutes and then you spend
two minutes again to just copy paste
what I said into cloud and like iterate,
right? So I just don't want to do that,
right? It's the the asymmetry is the
problem.
>> It's also a context switching, right?
Like as a maintainer, everyone thinks
it's just about going writing your open
source code, writing your open source
code, shipping your open source code.
But really it's a much bigger like
social question. You have people asking
you about problems with your code all
the time. You're trying to communicate
how your code works to all of them with
your documentation. You get
contributions. And so every time you get
these contributions, you are stopping
like I I spend more of my maintaining
time looking at code, figuring out what
the bigger problems are than actually
going and writing code. And so this like
30 minutes to three hours is completely
true and it like just grows and grows
and grows as the volume grows.
>> We are we are we are converging into bad
cop good cop, I think, like that.
So there is some quotes from different
maintainers. For instance, some of the
SymPy maintainers put this into very
explicit terms that
it really feels like this, right?
Because because we we have very little
resources, right? Many of us have like
our own jobs that are related or
unrelated to that. So we do this already
on our hobby time and it's just like we
already have responsibilities to do, but
like now it's just it's just impossible
to stop. Also, there is all this push
for people to do it. So and now there is
a lot of push as well for getting
contributors into open source as a way
to get reputation. We will look at that
later. So now there is even more, you
know, incentives for for people to to
push uh even more. Um do you want to
play in the pond?
>> Uh yeah, so this was one of the stats
that I was going to present in my talk.
Um it was an article that I saw back in
February, so already slightly out of
date given how fast things change now.
Um it was an article titled Cloud Code
is the inflection point. And what it's
showing is the number of commits that
Cloud Code is generating on GitHub. And
that point at February this year is 4%
of public commits. And I guess you can
see how fast it's growing every month.
We might be on 6, 8, 10% by now. Um it's
kind of an astonishing number. And the
article was basically reasoning that,
you know, at some point this is just
going to take over. It's going to be a
tool.
>> This is also partially, I mean,
obviously not not not officially
confirmed, but this is also partially
what Microsoft has the
dubious
like uh you know, um
honor to be the first major company with
like 09 like 19 of reliability in their
uh uptime. Uh
you know, you could you could argue that
perhaps they don't know what they're
doing, but like I believe that they know
what they're doing. I just believe that
they're being basically flooded by API
calls and they don't know how to deal
with this, right? Because, you know,
perhaps that's not an exponential, but
like if you squint a bit, it looks like
one. Um more numbers. Uh so it looks
like like unsurprisingly like almost
double of issues are being co-authored
by AI or written by AI directly. And we
are seeing like almost 91% increase in
code review time with high AI adoption.
So that means that PRs take even more
time to review because normally they are
bigger. Um the other thing is that uh
and this actually makes me extremely sad
is that uh the first issues are being
obliterated. Like I I I did this almost
10 times last week when I open a first
issue that I could just fix in a second,
right? Like myself, not even with Cloud
Code or uh
you know, uh colleagues or whatever. Uh
I'm I'm deliberately open it so someone
can pick it and learn something, right?
Perhaps someone who is starting to code
or something and they can think, "Oh, I
contributed to CPython. That's kind of
cool. And in the nanosecond I open the
issue there is a 3 million line PR
fixing a typo, right? So So and the
problem is that Yeah, exactly. So it's
horrible. And and yeah, yeah. And I mean
I was saying to David some some PR the
other day when like this happened it was
not an easy issue, but it happened and
someone submitted a 1 and 1/2 K added, 1
and 1/2 K deleted for one fix that was
literally 20 lines, right? So
and and you know, it was pretty obvious,
but like it's going to be less obvious
in the in the future that some PRs that
are, you know, maybe you will take it
because maybe it's that complex, but
then you think about it is just 20
lines, right? So um a lot of people are
complaining to the team that like they
don't have issues to start because they
are being taken over, right? But like at
incredible pace.
>> I think the patch you showed me was 26
lines including tests.
>> Yes, yes, exactly. Yeah, half of that,
right? Yeah.
>> And we see the same thing going on in
Pydantic, right? Like, you know, there
is an issue tracker with maybe 500
issues or whatever. A lot of them have
not moved for a long time cuz they're
hard problems. And then people are
throwing over like 2,000 line PRs every
other day cuz they just want to be the
contributor that also contributes to
Pydantic for that reputation boost that
we already established earlier.
>> Yeah, so so controversial. If you didn't
write it, do you own it? Of course like
this is, you know, a nuance and like
it's not really true, but like the the
the thing here is that um when you do
open source there is this I think Brett
Cannon put it into some very explicit
terms like when you make a PR it's like
a puppy, right? Like of course we love
puppies. Like puppies are cool, but then
you you give me a puppy and I need to
care care of the puppy, right? And the
puppy does a bunch of things that are
annoying. They're very annoying. But now
it's my puppy. And like you know, that's
not cool when I have 6 million puppies
over there that And one of them can be a
hacker, you know, like it's the one I
don't want hacker puppies. So so you
know, I know that you like your open
source thing, but like now, you know,
it's it's a bit more complicated because
the ownership is like fuzzy, right? And
And it's even more fuzzy if people don't
understand what they're submitting,
right? So so that's that's the other
thing. Uh And then and then that leads
us to security shenanigans. Security
shenanigans. So problems. Uh the the
kernel is flooded by security uh
vulnerabilities. Actually, this is even
outdated because we live in this world
where like everything is outdated in 10
seconds, like inflation in Argentina.
But like as far
But
the problem is that these guys, the
kernel maintainers are saying that
basically every day this past week, I
think they received 10 security
vulnerabilities that are correct
actually. So now they're not just like
not correct. That now they are correct.
And they cannot even deal with them. And
they are asking for other maintainers
that normally don't participate in
security vulnerabilities to to go there.
And in C Python, this is happening as
well. I mean, this is not true anymore
because the models actually now are
funding things. But for instance,
the the core maintainer, one of the core
the main core maintainer was saying that
as of February 2026, there is zero
really AI reports that were really cool
real. But like they they need to go
through all of them because you know,
the the the alternative is that one of
them is correct. And like people are
using it to hack because curl is
everywhere, right? It's even in your
toaster. Um
And and this is almost like he was
mentioning that this is DDoS to open
source because basically it's Saturday.
It's like you don't have a choice,
right? If you have a security
vulnerability, everybody gets hacked,
especially for something low level like
curl or C Python.
And and basically just it stops your
your your your your time because now you
you have to deal with this because of
course it's high priority. So but then
but then imagine your day, right? Like
you you you go to work and then you go
to this AI conference thing. And then
you review 6 million of these and it's
horrible. And then that that guy comes
with the puppy. It's like, "Oh, here's
the puppy." And then you say, "Fuck
off." You know? And then the guy is
like, "Oh, these guys are horrible."
Like like it's You know? And I feel
really bad because like I don't want to
be horrible. I I want to tell you, "No,
Mom. We don't get puppies because you
know." But like but but this is really
bad. And we are getting DDoS. That's how
it feels.
>> It's worth really stressing the point
about the AI vulnerability thing as
well, right? Because Oh, sorry. Of
vulnerabilities in general. Because when
you encounter these software like
vulnerabilities, you want to action
them. You want to close them. But
typically, finding software
vulnerabilities has been hard. Now, with
AI, what seems to be the case is that
yes, there's a lot of rubbish, but
there's also it's quite easy to find
vulnerabilities. So even worse, if
you're shipping your open source
software, how many vulnerabilities in
are in there that hackers might be
exploiting? It's like a volume that you
can't even answer right now. It's doubly
terrifying.
>> Indeed. Um so, this is the other problem
that makes this extremely sad.
I don't know if you like follow the exit
exit exit thing. Um so, but the problem
is that now maintainers especially of
our lower level project, every PR is a
vector, right? And now with the eye like
this can be a four-dimensional chess
movement in which like you are not just
making a PR that's compromised, you're
making like 20 PRs with different users
that now are super sophisticated in such
a way that like when you put it
together, it just basically hacks it
into a way that makes a large turning
the programming vector or whatever it
is. So, now, you know, the puppy is a
hacker puppy. It's a robotic hacker
puppy. It's a Trojan horse. So, now now
it's horrible because the the
interaction is not only asymmetrical,
but now it's antagonistic. Like now now
I'm looking at you like
Are you are you going to hack me, right?
And it just has such a horrible thing,
right? Because as a contributor, I
remember when I started to contribute,
and it was such an important thing for
me that like the the maintainers that
that review my PRs were nice to me like
in a way that like you know, I felt
appreciated and my work mattered. But
now, we live in a world where like
probably, you know,
you know, people people are not stupid.
Like you will you will see that your
work is being scrutinized and like
people are trying to figure out what
kind of person you are. And now as the
barrier between bots and humans like
probably even more, we don't know if if
things are human or not in PRs, then
those first impressions which matter a
lot are going to be harder, right? Like
because like now, you know, like you you
can see it like people will start
asking, "Are you a human?" And then the
thing will say, "Of course, I'm a human
called like global 667."
You know, like
>> Absolutely. I mean, what can I say?
Co-pilot code reviews will save you.
>> Yes. Yes. Uh
All right.
The the other thing is that
like when the PRs get bigger because the
LLMs like produce a lot of code very
quickly, like even the automatic
detection, even the themselves like
become like like less effective. In
particular because like, you know, most
of the
code review that is done by LLMs, unless
you put a stupid amount of iteration on
it, it looks like, well, if the user
unplugged the off the cable, this
crashes. And they're like, oh yes, yes,
yes, of course. But then you need to do
this like mega iteration when you burn 6
trillion nuclear power plants just to
get something that actually is useful.
But people keep submitting bigger PRs,
so like it's less and less useful,
right? So that that's a problem because
it's not a scaling at the same time.
Like LLMs can generate code faster than
LLMs can actually review properly code.
So unfortunately, we are still in the
like the human in the loop is the is the
barrier. And this is this is another
interesting metric, which is like 96% of
developers actually don't trust
AI-generated code,
which is kind of like shocking because
like I'm pretty sure a lot of those
people are using it. Um, you know, think
about it.
Um, so so that that's a bit scary. And a
lot of this is accidental actually. Uh,
the the thing is that a lot of these
bots are actually farming GitHub
reputation, right? Because because if
you think about it, if you are a person
that is known in the community or you
you, you know, I do this all the time
when I am a maintainer, right? Someone
opens a PR and like I have seen not this
person ever, it even says first
contributor. I I want some signal, so I
just click on the profile, I see what
else has happened and it says, oh, this
has contributed to bio 3. Okay, okay, I
see like a nice interaction, so I I I
trust this person more. So so it's in
their interest to to do this properly,
so like subsequent like iterations can
be
kind of like less scrutinized. You will
say, dude, like this is so paranoid
mode. Exactly. Like you see, because
like now like think about the exit
thing. It was like 3 years of being a
maintainer and being nice to the guy and
like like making the guy like give them
maintainer rights because of the mental
health thing. So people that want to
really do it and especially for
something like CPython and low-level
dependencies, like they don't mind, you
know, like spending time and effort and
years into it. So so being paranoid
unfortunately is the only way to like
stop some of this thing.
>> Yeah, absolutely. I mean, first thing I
do when I get an issue or a PR is quite
often I just like click on that profile
portrait and be like, "Oh, cool. Like,
you know, like, oh, you're kind of a
beginner. Okay, cool. Let's figure this
out how to like to break this through
together. Oh, wow, you're super
experienced. Okay, I can like throw
jargon back at you and you're not going
to even mind like, you know, let's
converse." But, yeah, if it's all new
people or like bot people, it's hard to
tell. Like, we can't meet everyone in
person. Conferences and meetups are
super cool, but that doesn't scale to
everybody.
>> It's It's also very brutal if you think
about it because before one of the
things I mean, I work in very low-level
parts of CPython, mostly the compiler,
the C parser, etc. So, it was pretty
difficult before to kind of like fake
it, right? Like, if you come to me and
then I'm reviewing something and then
you say, "Well, have you tried with
logarithms?" Like, okay, I maybe maybe
you don't know what you're talking
about. But, now like it's super easy.
Okay, what do you think we should say
here? So, now now I'm just counting the
m dashes, you know?
How many m dashes are here? Oh, okay,
bold text and colon in bullet points.
I see. So, that's horrible because
people like my manager loves m dashes.
Like, I'm like all the time,
"Is he using Is he using Clojure to talk
to me?"
>> Uh
>> Secret, I've always written with dashes,
but I've never been bothered to I've
never
I've never actually used m dashes cuz
it's too complicated to like
>> Okay, yeah. And Markdown puts in like
two of them, which is like, yes.
>> Exactly. I just, you know, one. So, you
know, I've got typos all over my stuff,
but that's, you know, it's human.
>> Exactly. Exactly. So, poor poor people
don't like m dashes. The the biggest
loss. Uh
So, yes, like and the other thing is
this thing, right? Like, you know,
you you may think like, "Well, what our
problem?" But, like, the problem is that
uh
we start like feeling like this more and
more, right? Like, our ability to care
is actually quite scarce. And like, we
this is a global resource that is
depleting. Uh there is a more sad slide
later. But, uh you know, the thing is
that this is a race between how
motivated we can be as maintainers and
like how demotivated we can be by this
flood of different things that are
happening around us.
>> Um yeah. I mean, I think there's a slide
later on I want to talk to you more on
this theme. Yeah.
>> Do you want to take this one?
>> Uh, yeah. I mean, so this was one of the
big points that I was going to make in
my talk, right? That trust is something
that gets established over a long time,
and it's so important to what we do in
software development. Like, you know,
you choose to take on a a dependency in
your code. You typically want to order
that dependency, work out whether you
trust it. And that's something that you
judge by the people who are working on
it. How long has that project been
around? How big is it? And, you know,
with all of this volume growing and
growing and growing, it's something that
also the maintainers are now having this
problem. They can't trust the people
that are coming to them. And so, it's
like a problem that we have facing us
very, like, coherently, but also
something that is potentially an
opportunity for us to think about, like,
how do we go from here and establish
what trust looks like as this all
changes. And if we can do that right,
maybe there's positive outcomes to come
from this point.
>> Exactly.
So, and this is the thing, right? Like,
I think this is like the how this
question is like the genie's out of the
bottle, and like, we cannot just say,
"Well, open source is done." Like, we we
won't do it, but because like, we we we
we like our projects. We like open
source. Like, we must fight for it,
right? And, you know, it's very easy to
just say, "Well, you know, everything is
broken and whatnot." But like, I think
there is a way. It's just like it's it's
very difficult to find like the narrow
path. Like, what what is the path here?
And I think like, talking to David here
and like, to Samuel before and like, to
a lot of maintainers, the the thing is
that all the common thing that I'm
seeing is that nobody knows really like
what how to fix this. Like, it's just
like, you know, we we see that we have
common problems together, um, but all
the alternative kind of suck in some
way, which like Okay. Uh, but and and
this is just to be clear, I'm I'm not
insisting on the bright parts of all of
this because there is a lot of bright
parts, right? Like, there's a lot of
stupid things that I don't want to do,
but now I can just do like this and it's
amazing. Like, I I just love this,
right? So, so I I I just think there is
so much optimism around it that I don't
need to enforce it. So, that's why I'm
being slightly more uh, pessimistic here
in this particular talk. But, of course,
like, this has a such a huge uplift.
Like, I'm pretty sure projects like
Monty uh, before would have taken so
many years of planning and probably not
even worth it. And now, you know, the
fact that you know, you can you can
iterate so quickly and create that much
value is very useful and like negating
that will be stupid. It's just that now
there's this weird balance when like
it's unclear how to, you know, merge
both things in such a way that we can
move forward.
>> Yeah, absolutely. I think Samuel first
talked to me about the idea of a Python
interpreter in Rust back when I started
with Pydantic like 3 years ago or
something. And then like yeah, it
basically built Monty over the Christmas
holidays last year,
more or less.
>> That's very cool. It would be the the
second interpreter in Rust, no? Like
>> Yeah.
>> I don't know. CPython maybe most Rust as
well. Uh okay, well but sad sad sad sad.
Let's let's move to the sadness. Okay,
so so just in the interest of time. So,
the just just just to be clear what we
are thinking of losing.
The problem is that we I think we are
losing open source as we know it. I
think this sounds very sad and it's sad
it just it just breaks my soul, but I
think something will born like will be
born out of this. I I hope it's
something great and I will certainly be
there because I still like open source,
but I don't think like the time when you
could make a PR and put like your
weekend on that and then become a
maintainer, I think that's gone. Like
I'm so sorry like to to break it to you,
but I think that's gone. And something
else will have to be born out of this
and because like we need to move on. But
like what how it looks like, I don't
know. Like I'm pretty sure there are
like cool parts about this because, you
know, you can think if you are extremely
optimistic, you can think a world where
like nobody wants to hack anything and
all the puppies like are amazing and
well-behaved and we can have so many
puppies now, you know, like amazing.
That that's very cool.
There is a lot of issues that I know
fixing because I don't even have the 3
minutes that it takes to close code the
issue or like
code exit the issue out. So, it would be
amazing if like none of this happens.
It's just like we need to deal with this
before so we can have the other thing,
right? And that's the thing that we
don't know how to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, as I'm quoting the creator of
Go CT I think
mentioned it quite well. The problem is
that there is there is no back pressure
right now to how low effort is to make
contributions right now. So, we need
First, we need some way of filter. Like
so, the the the the first thing that we
need to do is like there's a lot of slop
that we can remove. And then there's a
lot of like we're like in the middle
kind of thing that probably we need to
learn how to remove and that's going to
be really hard. But we need some kind of
filter to or back pressure to push back
against this. So, like what actually
reaches our time and the time of people
uh that involved like is exactly what
needs to be reviewed. In that way, you
are always thinking that you're moving
forward or you're talking to humans and
you don't need to have these weird
interactions with like potential robots.
>> Yeah. Um I should possibly point out at
that point though that like I'm what
guilty of potentially becoming part of
the slop myself, right? Because as an
open source maintainer, I deal with a
lot of other software and a lot of other
projects. Typically, I would go look at
those other projects and be like, I
don't have enough context to help here.
Whereas now I'm like, "Hmm, I've hit
your bug. I'm just going to like, you
know, drive-by PR for you and hope that
my reputation carries me through."
Really, that's not a good answer cuz
like really it's I'm just going to
produce more slop for you to go and make
train and do your 3 hours of code review
or whatever whatever, figure out who I
am. Am I trying to be a secure security
hacker for you? So, yeah, it's a
problem. There's no easy filtering.
>> Yeah.
>> The the other thing I think you you I
think is very difficult for us is that
before when we kind of like, you know,
future maintainers were contributors at
the beginning, right? And and like there
is a there was a pipeline or at least
there is maybe right now as well where
like contributors become maintainers.
And the way it work, of course, is like,
you know, someone will make a change and
then you will you will help them and
then the person the person is engaged on
what not. And part of what drive that is
precisely the effort of the other
person. Like in the sense that if I have
a person who wants to, you know, fix
this thing and you know, he's responsive
and he's clearly putting some effort,
there's this human thing in the brain
that says, "Hmm, I must reciprocate."
So, you put the effort on your side and
it creates like a a connection.
>> And also that like those first
contributions by future maintainers are
typically like super small things,
right? They're like fix a few typos or
like help with a very very small
specific patch. Pablo talked about the
good first issues earlier and like when
I became an open source maintainer it
was much the same thing. I think
everything I first contributed to PyO3,
I've since ripped out because it was all
rubbish, but you know, like that's how I
became an open source contributor once
upon a time and that opportunity is
possibly not there anymore.
>> Yeah, no, I mean that's an excellent
point. Like my first contributed to
CPython was a typo. I mean that's it's
it's true and then I changed the entire
version of the language, you know, very
scary. Uh but that that that's that's
something that is broken right now
because 2 minutes, well, I think I can
do it.
Uh but the the problem is that it's
broken right now because the effort is
gone. Like like now someone puts in
front of me 2,000 lines of code and I
I'm not thinking like wow, what a what
an impressive work. Like now, you may I
don't know, use code code whatever. So
now there's no connection anymore. So
there is no no no thing to keep and like
graph to to create the connection. It's
really really hard and you're not going
to have a zoom call to with every
contributor to know they're real and
establish that thing. So now we are like
islands and the islands are getting like
farther apart and like we we are we are
we are hanging with these tiny ropes
that are breaking and it's very sad to
see how the ropes break and I think one
of the biggest challenges that we are
going to have right now is how to, you
know, keep those ropes from breaking
breaking or just, you know, find I don't
know, laser ropes or something.
Cool. I think because we have 2 minutes
we are going to do this
and then, you know, bunk. Oh, wow,
finished. I mean when I was just me it
was easy because, you know, I speak
really really fast. Uh
Sorry, it's your fault.
>> I'll try to speak as fast as
>> No, no, I mean amazing. Sorry and thank
you for participating. Uh
No, thanks. Thanks a lot. Uh
you know, I I mean he had a 5-minute
talk and like I you know, you you put
this effort into going with me which is
not easy. So I'm I'm very grateful. Uh
but yes, okay. So so let let let let let
let do a summary lifting so these people
don't don't like exit crying. I think I
think this is great. Like I'm very
excited nevertheless. Uh it's just that
yes, yes, I'm very excited nevertheless
because I do think we have now the time
to do something that we couldn't do
before. Because before like a lot of our
time was not dealing with like robots or
what not. It was dealing with a lot of
stupid things that are now can be done
in one minute. So a lot of my time have
actually been freed.
Unfortunately filled with other stuff
but like
because
I don't need to deal with that thing.
And the project is so much healthier
because you know humans also make bugs,
right? And then I we can see we are
seeing places when AI was extremely
well, like extremely well. And like even
getting first versions of PRs, which is
like sometimes the the bottleneck as
maintainers when someone comes to the
PR, makes a first review, and that means
that I can go over and like focus on
very specific details. Like now that
that's much easier. Like they can be
even like automated, right? So we can
focus on other things like manual
testing or even like the the mentoring
part because like we don't need to
dedicate that many cycles. It's just
that right now that doesn't work really
well. But maybe maybe like in a year is
a different story when like really this
like, you know, LLMs can be really
really reviewing code and we can focus
on the actual cool part. So I'm I'm
really hopeful that where we are going.
I think that the feeling that I'm
getting right now is not so
such a, you know, like despair. It's
mostly like, you know, disappointing
that we don't know where to move right
now. We are very confused right now that
we someone hit us in the head and we
don't know the direction we need to go
and we were not used to that. Like we we
used to have like a nice North Star that
we were following. And you know, it
would be very easy to come here to you
and say like well, I used to say I am a
legend 6 time million more productive
and blah blah blah. But I think more
fair to say like hey, I'm human and I'm
very confused and I don't know what
we're doing. So just bear with us,
right? Like if we go to you and you
submit a PR closed or not
and then we are like a bit grumpy. So
sorry. I mean we are doing our best. So
so just iterate a bit. Just just I don't
know prove that you're human or
something.
And then you know, that you understand
the situation and just just just be a
bit more patient these these months and
years perhaps with open source
maintainers because we will get through
it. We will get uh to some cool place.
We just need some time to figure it out.
>> I see.
>> Uh maybe just something for the room.
Have we thought about sort of
establishing a chain of trust for
contributors? So, to remove the
remove the auto-generated slop.
And kind of go, "Hey, I know you. I know
you. I know you. So, then if I submit
at least there's some chain involved
here so you can validate
not a random somebody trying to hack
you.
>> So, um I have seen I mean I have a few
different thoughts about this. One is
that I think one of the fantastic things
about open source historically has been
that it's been so easy for anybody to
come along. You don't You don't need to
be part of the club as it were to become
a member of open source. So, gatekeeping
in that way feels super dangerous to my
principles of what I used to know.
At the same time, like I've seen that
sort of need seems to happen. Do you
have like an email spam filter type
mechanism for pull requests? Like that
feels a bit of a shame if you know
someone legitimate puts loads of effort
in and then the slop filter cuts it out.
So, it's a really hard issue to think
about how to do with a personal touch.
Um on the other side, like that vouching
thing. So, Seth um Larson, the um
CPython security expert, he has uh I've
seen a blog post from him about I can't
remember what it's called now, but some
sort of human
attestation that he basically puts on
his website and it's a list of himself
and others who he he attests as a human.
And you know, they individually have a
like JSON file or whatever it is
reachable on their domain which attests
them and more people. So, you know,
they're trying to build a social graph
out of all of those attestations if you
like, kind of like what you describe,
but I'm kind of having engaged in that
myself for the caution against that kind
of gatekeeping effect.
>> I I the gatekeeping comment and it's
like at least we have a rich community
where people can just turn up
>> Yeah.
>> at various meetups around all of the
world. And you know, like if you go back
a couple of decades, have a good
old-fashioned GPG key signing party.
>> I I just just to complement this, I
think
Carl mentioned this in San Francisco.
The other thing I think is quite
important is that
there there are certain
like misrepresented people have
historically a very hard time to enter
for different reasons, right? And
it's precisely and even in the US term,
like that's quite like the newest. And I
feel this myself, like like I was
telling David before that like I think
the last eight persons that I have
mentored have been people in this
regard. So, they have mentioned how hard
it is. And like if you put more
barriers, that is risking more. But I I
I just to be clear, I don't think we
have a choice here. Like it's just like
we need to learn how to like fix it in
some other way. But like
some filter must be in place. The
problem is like how do you make it such
that first people that have like a
harder time entering the the community
don't don't even hurt even more because
they are unbalanced of the situation.
The second one is the same thing as like
junior people entering the industry
right now. It's just brutal. Like I
mean, just talk to them. It's just a
brutal mega competitive thing where like
nobody wants to hire juniors because
like, you know, why I can just use this
thing that does even more and you know,
it works 24 hours. But someone needs to
be the seniors of the future, you know?
So, like there is a problem here, and
those people are the ones that there is
no one to say that they are human, you
know, or like in this regard or like to
vouch for them because it's like, okay,
I
I was not born when this was being in
place, you know? So, I don't want to
forget about those people because those
are the ones that have the the highest
potential because it does like
the smaller change there can have the
biggest impact in the sense that if you
are already a person that is known, and
you want to contribute to some project,
and the project doesn't accept you.
Like, you know, you have your thing. You
don't need to to to go over there. But,
like, if you if it's the first project
that you want to contribute and you're
trying to see if open source is your
thing, it's so important that first
thing is so important. It's just so
delicate. It's just like a small thing
that you just destroy it, it just goes
away. And like something like a filter
will just obliterate that and, you know,
thinking if that's something that we
need to
avoid or is something that we need to
overcome from the other side is is
something that I don't know still what
is the solution.
>> This also highlights the importance of
having
events and more things for beginners and
for underrepresented minorities and for,
you know, the folks that
have not made that first PR yet. But,
anyway, um the broken hash because I
really wanted to rant more with you. I'm
enjoying this very much. But, uh so,
thank you so much. Um I appreciate
everybody that joined us. Uh thank you
very much to our speakers. And again,
thank you all. Uh enjoy uh engineering.
I'll see you next time.
>> Thank you.